<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Scrum on Software Craftsmanship and Agile Development</title>
    <link>http://codurance.com/tags/scrum/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Scrum on Software Craftsmanship and Agile Development</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2010 08:18:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://codurance.com/tags/scrum/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The relationship between Product Owner, Business Analyst and Tester</title>
      <link>http://codurance.com/blog/the-relationship-between-product-owner-business-analyst-and-tester/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2010 08:18:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://codurance.com/blog/the-relationship-between-product-owner-business-analyst-and-tester/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In an Agile/Scrum team the Product Owner manages the Product Backlog, a Business Analyst may help further elaborate the backlog. Acceptance Criteria is &amp;ldquo;one of the&amp;rdquo; or the output of that elaboration. A Tester may futher define the Acceptance Criteria and write test scripts to verify it. What is the relationship between the three roles? Inseparable, acquaintance or in a love triangle?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thoughts spring from the fact that I have frequently seen a gap between the tester and BA/Product Owner&amp;rsquo;s understanding of the requirements. I accept that the BA comes from the business perspective and the tester from the system/specification perspective. How can the two reach the same understanding of what the end system will deliver?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using JIRA for Agile Project Management (without Green Hopper)</title>
      <link>http://codurance.com/blog/using-jira-for-agile-project-management-without-green-hopper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2010 14:28:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://codurance.com/blog/using-jira-for-agile-project-management-without-green-hopper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.atlassian.com/software/jira/&#34;&gt;Jira&lt;/a&gt; from Atlassian  is a very popular issue tracking software and can be quite effectively used for Agile Project Management. Jira has a plugin (Green Hopper) that allows for creation of a backlog, iterations and tasks.  However, with help from the free Mylyn plugin for Eclipse I was able to setup a Product Backlog and Iteration Backlogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the User Stories in the product backlog I created two issue types (Epic &amp;amp; User Story).  Story hierarchies can be represented using Jira Links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;_Note: Currently Jira connector in Mylyn has an issue with the &amp;ldquo;depends on&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;is depended on by&amp;rdquo; relationships. It displays them the wrong way around in the Tasklist hierarchy.  You can keep track of the following issues to see if they&amp;rsquo;re fixed: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/show_bug.cgi?id=255680&#34;&gt;255680&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/show_bug.cgi?id=223151&#34;&gt;223151.&lt;/a&gt;_&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Iteration Backlog I created a version for each iteration and assigned the stories to that version/iteration. Each leaf story can then have Jira Sub-tasks to represent the tasks in a particular iteration. The &lt;code&gt;Resolved&lt;/code&gt; state of the story is used to mark it complete and &lt;code&gt;Colsed&lt;/code&gt; state is used to mark it as &amp;ldquo;accepted&amp;rdquo;. You can use Mylyn to see story hierarchies, also I found Mylyn to be a much more intuitive interface when working on Product and Iteration backlogs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>