<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Teamcity on Software Craftsmanship and Agile Development</title>
    <link>http://codurance.com/tags/teamcity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Teamcity on Software Craftsmanship and Agile Development</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://codurance.com/tags/teamcity/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Docker meets Continuous Deployment</title>
      <link>http://codurance.com/blog/docker-meets-continuous-deployment/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://codurance.com/blog/docker-meets-continuous-deployment/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;About one year ago I had my first contact with Docker. This new kid on the block promised to relieve our poor computers from installation of all tools, languages, dependencies and operating systems. Isolated run environments emerged on developers&amp;rsquo; computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While my ops teammates chose a more conservative approach, I started to use Docker with great joy. Despite many people describing Docker as a tool written by developers for development, our industry found new ways of using images and containers. Images of our applications and services became deployment units for tools like Kubernetes, Docker Swarm or Marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how are these images created?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;setting-the-scene&#34;&gt;Setting The Scene&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a developer&amp;rsquo;s perspective, any application is manifested by its code, but there is still a long way to go before this code finds its way to a production environment. I want to show you how this process can be easier with &lt;strong&gt;Docker&lt;/strong&gt; and a &lt;strong&gt;Continuous Deployment&lt;/strong&gt; pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all we need a small application with a HTTP API that we can call after it&amp;rsquo;s deployed. Let&amp;rsquo;s assume that we are using &lt;strong&gt;Gradle&lt;/strong&gt; to build the application and &lt;strong&gt;TeamCity&lt;/strong&gt; as a Continuous Integration server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to have &lt;strong&gt;Docker&lt;/strong&gt; installed on each &lt;strong&gt;TeamCity&lt;/strong&gt; build agent. We will also use this machine to run our application. In a real project we wouldn&amp;rsquo;t install &lt;strong&gt;TeamCity&lt;/strong&gt; agents on all machines. Instead we should use tools like Kubernetes that will take care of the application distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;build&#34;&gt;Build&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a first step in our Continuous Deployment pipeline, before we even think about Docker images, we need to build our application. In this step we will download the source code, run all &lt;strong&gt;tests&lt;/strong&gt; and produce an &lt;strong&gt;artifact&lt;/strong&gt; containing all elements required to start and run our application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This build configuration is not very different to a step in a Continuous Deployment pipeline without &lt;strong&gt;Docker&lt;/strong&gt;. Alongside common parameters we have to define &lt;strong&gt;artifacts&lt;/strong&gt;, which will be generated after each build run. We are going to use them as a base for next steps in the pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;TeamCity&lt;/strong&gt; we define &lt;strong&gt;artifacts&lt;/strong&gt; by defining paths to files from the working directory (which is created for each run of a configuration). The working directory is a combination of the files downloaded from a version control system and the files generated during the execution of build steps. The working directory elements are defined in the version control settings and build steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need two artifacts. The first one is &lt;code&gt;Dockerfile&lt;/code&gt;. We already prepared this file in our source code and it will be stored in the &lt;code&gt;docker&lt;/code&gt; directory.
The next file is a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;tar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; file which will be generated by our &lt;strong&gt;Gradle&lt;/strong&gt; build. It contains a script that executes our code and all required libraries.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;img src=&#34;http://codurance.com/assets/img/custom/blog/2016-03-01-docker-meets-continuous-deployment/build_config.png&#34; alt=&#34;Build Configuration&#34; title=&#34;Build Configuration&#34; class=&#34;img img-responsive style-screengrab&#34;/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now we are ready to instruct our build configuration how to download our source code. We use GitHub as our code repository, so we just have to choose &lt;em&gt;Git&lt;/em&gt; as the type of our &lt;strong&gt;Version Control System&lt;/strong&gt; and provide the URL to our application.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;img src=&#34;http://codurance.com/assets/img/custom/blog/2016-03-01-docker-meets-continuous-deployment/build_vcs.png&#34; alt=&#34;Version Control Configuration&#34; title=&#34;Version Control Configuration&#34; class=&#34;img img-responsive style-screengrab&#34;/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;With the source code in our working directory we can describe what to do with it. As I mentioned before we run all the &lt;strong&gt;tests&lt;/strong&gt; and generate an &lt;strong&gt;artifact&lt;/strong&gt; containing the start script and libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TeamCity&lt;/strong&gt; has predefined runners for different build tools. In this case we are going to use the &lt;strong&gt;Gradle&lt;/strong&gt; runner to &lt;strong&gt;test&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;build&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;img src=&#34;http://codurance.com/assets/img/custom/blog/2016-03-01-docker-meets-continuous-deployment/build_step.png&#34; alt=&#34;Gradle Step&#34; title=&#34;Gradle Step&#34; class=&#34;img img-responsive style-screengrab&#34;/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now we can run our build and as a result we should see our &lt;strong&gt;artifacts&lt;/strong&gt; in the &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Artifacts&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; tab.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;img src=&#34;http://codurance.com/assets/img/custom/blog/2016-03-01-docker-meets-continuous-deployment/build_result.png&#34; alt=&#34;Build Result&#34; title=&#34;Build Result&#34; class=&#34;img img-responsive style-screengrab&#34;/&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;release&#34;&gt;Release&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our code is no longer needed. We have all we need to build the docker image. Now we have to create our image and &lt;strong&gt;release&lt;/strong&gt; it with the right version. To simplify our example we are going to use the current build number to define an image version.
Next we will generate a file with this version. This file gives us the possibility to pass information about the version to the next steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take a closer look at the &lt;code&gt;Dockerfile&lt;/code&gt;. We copy the content of &lt;code&gt;simple_application.tar&lt;/code&gt; (which contains all required libraries and scripts) to the image, by using the &lt;code&gt;ADD&lt;/code&gt; command. This command will automatically &lt;em&gt;untar&lt;/em&gt; all files inside the image. Next we expose the port of our HTTP API and we define how to launch our application by adding an &lt;code&gt;ENTRYPOINT&lt;/code&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example our &lt;code&gt;Dockerfile&lt;/code&gt; can look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34;&gt;FROM java:8

ADD simple_application.tar .

EXPOSE 4567

ENTRYPOINT [&amp;quot;/simple_application/bin/simple_application&amp;quot;]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defining the build configuration is very simple. In general settings we define a new artifact: &lt;code&gt;image.version&lt;/code&gt;. The content of this file will be generated in the one of the build steps.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;img src=&#34;http://codurance.com/assets/img/custom/blog/2016-03-01-docker-meets-continuous-deployment/release_config.png&#34; alt=&#34;Release Configuration&#34; title=&#34;Release Configuration&#34; class=&#34;img img-responsive style-screengrab&#34;/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Without the &lt;strong&gt;artifact&lt;/strong&gt; we won&amp;rsquo;t be able to build any image. We have to tell our build how to find the &lt;strong&gt;artifacts&lt;/strong&gt; generated during the &lt;strong&gt;Build&lt;/strong&gt; phase. We can do that by defining an &lt;strong&gt;Artifact Dependency&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;TeamCity&lt;/strong&gt;. We just have to choose a build configuration, define the &lt;strong&gt;artifacts&lt;/strong&gt; from that build and &lt;strong&gt;TeamCity&lt;/strong&gt; will add them to the working directory.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;img src=&#34;http://codurance.com/assets/img/custom/blog/2016-03-01-docker-meets-continuous-deployment/release_artifacts.png&#34; alt=&#34;Release Artifact Dependency&#34; title=&#34;Release Artifact Dependency&#34; class=&#34;img img-responsive style-screengrab&#34;/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And finally we have to trigger this build automatically after all &lt;strong&gt;tests&lt;/strong&gt; run by the previous step pass. By introducing &lt;strong&gt;Finish Build Trigger&lt;/strong&gt; we can start this build just after &lt;strong&gt;TeamCity&lt;/strong&gt; successfully finishes building the application.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;img src=&#34;http://codurance.com/assets/img/custom/blog/2016-03-01-docker-meets-continuous-deployment/release_trigger.png&#34; alt=&#34;Release Trigger&#34; title=&#34;Release Trigger&#34; class=&#34;img img-responsive style-screengrab&#34;/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now we are ready for a release. Three build steps must be introduced: &lt;strong&gt;Build Image&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Push Image&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Save Version&lt;/strong&gt;.
This time we will use a different runner type: &lt;strong&gt;Command Line&lt;/strong&gt;. We can execute a shell script on a build agent. Because we have already installed &lt;strong&gt;Docker&lt;/strong&gt; on our build agent we can use the &lt;code&gt;docker&lt;/code&gt; command in our shell script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;build-image&#34;&gt;Build Image&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To build the image we need to execute the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;docker build --tag registry.private/simple_application:%build.number% .
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Docker&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;build&lt;/code&gt; command will take our &lt;code&gt;Dockerfile&lt;/code&gt; and build the image tagged as &lt;code&gt;registry.private/simple_application&lt;/code&gt; and the version &lt;code&gt;%build.number%&lt;/code&gt;.
The variable &lt;code&gt;%build.number%&lt;/code&gt; is a built-in &lt;strong&gt;TeamCity&lt;/strong&gt; variable containing the current build number.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;img src=&#34;http://codurance.com/assets/img/custom/blog/2016-03-01-docker-meets-continuous-deployment/release_step_1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Release Build Image Step&#34; title=&#34;Release Build Image Step&#34; class=&#34;img img-responsive style-screengrab&#34;/&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;push-image&#34;&gt;Push Image&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image created in the previous step exists only on the agent machine. To make the image available to others we need to store it in a repository. We can use &lt;strong&gt;Docker Hub&lt;/strong&gt;, but in our example we use a private repository available under the address &lt;code&gt;repository.private&lt;/code&gt;. We can execute the following command to push the image to the repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;docker push registry.private/simple_application:%build.number%
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;img src=&#34;http://codurance.com/assets/img/custom/blog/2016-03-01-docker-meets-continuous-deployment/release_step_2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Release Push Image to Repository Step&#34; title=&#34;Release Push Image to Repository Step&#34; class=&#34;img img-responsive style-screengrab&#34;/&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;save-version&#34;&gt;Save Version&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image is safely stored in the repository, but we need to do one more step: save the version of our image. Once again we run a shell script to generate an &lt;code&gt;image.version&lt;/code&gt; file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;echo %build.number% &amp;gt; image.version
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;img src=&#34;http://codurance.com/assets/img/custom/blog/2016-03-01-docker-meets-continuous-deployment/release_step_3.png&#34; alt=&#34;Release Save Version Step&#34; title=&#34;Release Save Version Step&#34; class=&#34;img img-responsive style-screengrab&#34;/&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;deploy&#34;&gt;Deploy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous step we created an image which we can use now to deploy our application. We are going to create another build configuration: &lt;strong&gt;Deploy&lt;/strong&gt;. This build will run a Docker container on the &lt;strong&gt;TeamCity&lt;/strong&gt; agent based on the image from the &lt;strong&gt;Release&lt;/strong&gt; phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our build configuration must contain three elements. The first one is a trigger. Again, we use the &lt;strong&gt;Finish Build Trigger&lt;/strong&gt; with a dependency to the &lt;strong&gt;Release&lt;/strong&gt; build configuration.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;img src=&#34;http://codurance.com/assets/img/custom/blog/2016-03-01-docker-meets-continuous-deployment/deploy_trigger.png&#34; alt=&#34;Deploy Trigger&#34; title=&#34;Deploy Trigger&#34; class=&#34;img img-responsive style-screengrab&#34;/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second element is a version string of our image. We can obtain this information from the &lt;strong&gt;artifact&lt;/strong&gt; created by the &lt;strong&gt;Release&lt;/strong&gt; build.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;img src=&#34;http://codurance.com/assets/img/custom/blog/2016-03-01-docker-meets-continuous-deployment/deploy_artifact.png&#34; alt=&#34;Deploy Artifact&#34; title=&#34;Deploy Artifact&#34; class=&#34;img img-responsive style-screengrab&#34;/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The last step is a little bit more complicated. Before we deploy the new version of the application the deployment script need to check if the container with the previous version is already deployed on the machine. If we have such a container we need to stop and remove it.
Next we read the current version from the &lt;strong&gt;artifact&lt;/strong&gt; and create the new container based this version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;if [ -n &amp;quot;$(docker ps --filter label=simple_application -q)&amp;quot; ]; then 
   docker stop simple_application
   docker rm simple_application
fi;

version_to_deploy=$(cat image.version)
docker run -d -p 80:4567 \
           --name simple_application \
           --label simple_application \
           registry.private/simple_application:${version_to_deploy}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;img src=&#34;http://codurance.com/assets/img/custom/blog/2016-03-01-docker-meets-continuous-deployment/deploy_step.png&#34; alt=&#34;Deploy Step&#34; title=&#34;Deploy Step&#34; class=&#34;img img-responsive style-screengrab&#34;/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The Continuous Deployment pipeline is ready. Now every change in the master branch of our repository will build, test, release and deploy our application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-s-done&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s done.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The continuous deployment pipeline described in this post is of course simplified. Between our &lt;strong&gt;Release&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Deploy&lt;/strong&gt; steps we would like to do some
additional tests on a production-like environment or introduce &lt;a href=&#34;http://codurance.com/services/training/devops-training/&#34;&gt;zero downtime deployments&lt;/a&gt;, but our approach to any deployment should remain unchanged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use the &lt;strong&gt;Docker&lt;/strong&gt; image. You can ensure a consistent execution environment for your application on every stage of the Continuous Deployment. Now you decide how the code is executed and you cannot blame admins anymore for installing a wrong version of Java or Ruby.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>