<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dreams on Software Craftsmanship and Agile Development</title>
    <link>http://codurance.com/tags/dreams/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dreams on Software Craftsmanship and Agile Development</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2015 14:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://codurance.com/tags/dreams/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why you should always follow your dreams!</title>
      <link>http://codurance.com/blog/Why-you-should-always-follow-your-dreams%21/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2015 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://codurance.com/blog/Why-you-should-always-follow-your-dreams%21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I started at &lt;a href=&#34;http://codurance.com/&#34;&gt;Codurance&lt;/a&gt; a month and a half ago as a C# developer. I was glad to have the opportunity to work in a place where people value your effort to be a better developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been away from C# for more than 4 years, but I was happy to return. This was for me a great opportunity to catch up with my main language. But my passion is with iOS. In my own time, I started to apply all the techniques that I&amp;rsquo;ve been learning, especially on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ananogal.com/blog/starting-your-tdd-journey/&#34;&gt;honing my TDD skills&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://codurance.com/2015/07/13/How-to-start-doing-TDD-in-iOS/&#34;&gt;applying TDD to iOS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why did I apply for C# and not iOS? Well, I looked for three months for a iOS company that could give me an opportunity. It was really hard. They all wanted senior developers who could get there and get the job done, but I&amp;rsquo;m not at that level in iOS yet. I still have a lot to learn and I needed an opportunity to learn more from experienced developers, exchange thoughts and understand how things work. Working in C#, I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with several clients, I know how to address a problem, and how I can put my expertise to help, but that&amp;rsquo;s not yet true when working on iOS projects. This kind of experience is what I missed from my journey in the world of apps. I&amp;rsquo;m the primary developer of 4 apps, but that wasn&amp;rsquo;t enough. I&amp;rsquo;ve deployed them all to the App Store, despite having to dedicate a whole day to it every time! But I was my own client. They all started as small pet projects that got big enough for me to stay at home for four years and try to make it work. I really loved it, but I missed the exchange  of experience in a team. This is what makes you grow in your profession. The great discussions that a subject can lead to…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So two weeks ago, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/sandromancuso&#34;&gt;Sandro&lt;/a&gt; mentioned that we had an opportunity in iOS. A client was willing to have me as an apprentice, if I could pass the interview. I was thrilled that I could pursue my dream! Given a choice between iOS or C#, I will always choose iOS, but I never thought that Codurance would help me fulfill my dream. I can definitely be more profitable in C# than in iOS, but Codurance choose to give me an opportunity to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since my first job, where I stayed for 7 years, I haven&amp;rsquo;t had the same feeling. I still say &amp;ldquo;my company&amp;rdquo; when I&amp;rsquo;m talking about them with friends. Since then I&amp;rsquo;ve worked in several companies not only in Portugal but also in Spain. None of them made me feel a team member or cared about my opinions. My colleagues have made me want to be a better person, not only a better developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh! by the way, I&amp;rsquo;ve done the interview and I started yesterday. ;-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last two weeks, I reviewed everything I learnt about software development and applied it to Objective-C. I&amp;rsquo;ve been learning a lot! Even doing katas has made me investigate and discover all sorts of new concepts and approaches. But that will be the topic for another blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you have a dream and you can&amp;rsquo;t pursue it right away, don&amp;rsquo;t lose the passion for it, and never ever put it in a drawer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>